A Guide to the Papers of Mark Twain, 1862-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Letters
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, [1886] June 16; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Announces return from journey to the Mississippi via the Lakes; says that Olivia is planning letter for Koto; discusses the secret language devised and used by Susy and Daisy Warner and hopes House will figure it out. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to Fred J. Hall, 1886 July 14; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Encloses letter from Mr. Howell (not present); will refer contents of letter to Alexander and Green and if they advise, wishes to instigate suit against John Wannamaker. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to Edward Howard House, 1886 July 26; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Apologizes to Koto for forgetting to send measurements; sends the "lingo letter" mentioned before; discusses Susy's and Daisy's writing styles. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1886 August 11; ALS, 9 p. (Box 2)
    Doubts Rooker's opinion; discusses (New York) Tribune's typesetting problems, the wearing of matrices and alignment of type, whether they might be fixed, and how much these problems cost the Tribune; claims the Paige typesetter is superior to all other invented typesetters; comments on Olivia's good opinion of House. In postscript; mentions Tribune's alignment problem solved and that they are using new matrices; attributes quick wear of matrices to design (includes sketch of matrix); plans to measure how long new set lasts. M.T.
  - Susy Clemens, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1886 August 14; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Thanks for House's note in the secret language of Susy and Daisy Warner, and for not telling her parents what it was; adds politely that House did make several errors in their secret language; mentions Jean pleased by dress Koto sent.
  - Susy Clemens, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1886 August 24; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Thanks House for another note and will send him their rules for the secret language if Daisy Warner agrees. Postscript in secret language.
  - Mark Twain to Unknown, [1886 August]; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Fragment. Gives joking account asserting he did not fall asleep in court during the John Wannamaker trial but fainted; urges correspondent to place story in newspapers. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to Edward Howard House, 1886 October 8; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Will come to visit House on Tuesday; Olivia says Twain must invite Mr. McCarthy (over Twain's prejudices) so asks House to give him the enclosed invitation. M.T.
  - Olivia L. Clemens, Hartford, CT, to [Emma] Beach, 1886 October 17; ALS, 4 p. (Box 2)
    Enjoyed her visit; would love for her (with Ellen) to visit them when the room is finished and invites Violet to stay with them overnight after attending a nearby wedding; Twain unhappy he could not join them on visit at Peekskill.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1886 October 18; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Points out that Stoddard's "The Brahman's Son" was not borrowed from House's story; suggests he check "Yamarajah" in Stray Leaves from Strange Literature with the poem line by line. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to [George E.] Waring [Jr.], 1886 November 6; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Has written the letter, but Olivia does not approve; she says he must consider Lowell's piece of mind and not press the matter at the Authors' Club; comments on women and reason. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1886 November 26; ALS, 3 p. (Box 2)
    Sympathizing with House in House and Koto's illnesses; says Olivia afraid if he were made House's executor, he might not do it well; suggests Franklin G. Whitmore instead and Twain could aid Whitmore in any way possible. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to [Edwin Pond] Parker, [1886] December 6; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Invitation to dine with Henry M. Stanley. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1886 December 17; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Remembers House had mentioned that The Prince and the Pauper would be nice dramatized; has tried it himself unsuccessfully; mentions House could try it for half to two thirds of the proceeds and might enjoy trying it when his pains abate a while; admits he is ashamed to be incapable of being House's executor. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1886 December 26; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Has ordered a couple of The Prince and the Pauper books to be sent to House; is sending his own attempt at dramatizing it; expects to see him soon. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to [William H.] Gross, 1887 January 20; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Places book orders. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to Mrs. Thornburgh, 1887 February 7; ALS, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Wishes he could help her but he is not acquainted much with journalism any more; has already written to the two journalists he does know, but they declined the request; glad Stewart is a senator; begs to be remembered to "once-little-girl" he used to know. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to [Richard Watson] Gilder, 1887 March 23; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Says unspecified article "first appeared in Galaxy magazine between May 1870 and April 1871"; proofs have not come. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to John Davis on PL titled "Copy of a letter written in answer to inquiries made by a personal friend", [1887 April 19]; ALS on PL, 2 p. (Box 2)
    Praises Loisette memory system; requests that Davis tell the Garths that the "d'UnLap" part of The Century article ("History of a Campaign that Failed") will not appear in The Century 's war book; mentions John Robards. S.L.C. In PL, Twain praises the Loisette memory system.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1887 May 5; ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
    Encourages House's plans to write about Japan; looks forward to seeing him soon. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to Edward Howard House, 1887 May 7; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Says to ship the wheelchair and make own arrangements for the luggage; will cancel an engagement to meet him.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to William L. Alden, 1887 May 28; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Thanks for a first chance at his autobiography; not sure what publishing prospects now would be but refers him to Charles L. Webster who is in charge of business part of the publishing house. S.L.C.
  - Clara Clemens to Edward Howard House, 1887 June 29; ALS, 3 p. (Box 3)
    So glad to get House's French, German and English letter and is trying to answer in kind; they miss him very much and love to Koto.
  - Susy Clemens, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1887 July 5; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Says they miss House and Koto; discusses Twain kittens and cat in Elmira.
  - Clara Clemens to Edward Howard House, 1887 July 14; ALS, 7 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses House's letters, seeing a manufacturing plant in Elmira burn, Fourth of July celebrations, her activities, and reading Dickens.
  - Susy Clemens, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1887 July [17?]; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses Twain cats and family news.
  - Clara Clemens to Edward Howard House, 1887 July 24; ALS, 5 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses neighborhood dogs, her activities, and House's letters; passing mention of House staying with Mrs. Warner and the Yosts.
  - Olivia L. Clemens, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1887 July 24; ALS, 5 p. (Box 3)
    Appreciates his letters to the children; discusses a letter of his she mislaid, his visiting plans and hiring a new nurse for Jean; looking forward to seeing him and Koto.
  - Susy Clemens to Edward Howard House, 1887 [August. 4?]; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses substitute suggested for profanity and news of family and friends.
  - Clara Clemens to Edward Howard House, 1887 August 9; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses House's letter; mentions the Day family, her activities, and family news.
  - Susy Clemens, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House, 1887 August 9; ALS, 6 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses the cold weather, her grandmother's [ Olivia Lewis Langdon] birthday, photo of Koto and Elize, visiting Mrs. [Clara Spaulding] Stanchfield's baby daughter, creating with Daisy Warner another secret language; wishes Koto and House could stay in Hartford all winter.
  - Susy Clemens, Elmira, NY, to Edward Howard House with AN n.d. by Edward Howard House, 1887 September [7]; ALS, 7 p. (Box 3)
    Will be leaving Elmira soon; describes her grandmother's party; plans to see play in New York; reports family busy discussing Bacon as Shakespeare; will write Koto soon. AN, in pencil by Edward Howard House, states Susy is answering his letter sent in same mail as one to Mark Twain, which Twain claims he did not receive.
  - Will [Mantz], Fresno, CA, to Sam[uel E. Moffett], 1887 [September 20] Monday; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Thanks him for letter of recommendation; has letter of recommendation from Prof. Bra[d]y to Judge North, who knows a lot about fruit and raisins; discusses railroad possibilities.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to [Robert Underwood] Johnson, 1887 October 31; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Agrees to do a reading and states stipulations. S.L.C.
  - Will [Mantz], Fresno, CA, to Sister [Mary Mantz Moffett], 1887 November 18; ALS, 20 p. (Box 3)
    Checking into farm prospects for Samuel E. Moffett in California; discusses fruit crops and farm properties at length.
  - Will [Mantz], Fresno, CA, to Sam[uel E. Moffett], 1887 November 20; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Re business matters, real estate, and farm.] (w/env)
  - Will [Mantz], Fresno, CA, to Sister [Mary Mantz Moffett], 188[7 ante November]; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Mentions expense of living in Fresno; discusses property of Samuel E. Moffett and family business matters.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to [Candace] Wheeler, 1888 April 19; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Turns down invitation to spend time with them in mountains; plans to keep Olivia in Elmira at the farm to get her better. S.L.C.
  - Olivia L. Clemens to Edward Howard House, 1888 July 9; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses House's dental matters and Susy and Clara's doings; hopes House's river "excursion" will be pleasant.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Andrew Chatto, 1888 July 15; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Believes no more bills will be sent but to forward them if they do; plans to ask Chatto's and Dawson's help in securing Canadian copyright for [Philip] Sheridan's book; thought and hoped Chatto would take Tauchnitz's offer. S.L.C.
  - Clara Clemens to Edward Howard House, 1888 July 19; ALS, 6 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses the weather, family activities, and what she is reading; mentions Theodore Crane; asks to be remembered to Koto.
  - Franklin G. Whitmore (for Mark Twain ) to Frank E. Bliss, 1888 October 9; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Twain has instructed him to tell Bliss he is correct in sending royalty statement and check directly to him; acknowledges receipt for $569.50 check.
  - Olivia L. Clemens to Edward Howard House, [1888 October 14]; ALS, 3 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses setting a date for Koto's visit to the Clemens family.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Fred J. Hall, 1888 November 12; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses a limited recommendation of a Mr. Wright who is apparently seeking employment from Hall; reports on his discussion with Mr. Wright. S.L.C.] (w/env.)
  - Olivia L. Clemens, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1888 December 9; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Thanks for the book; is glad to have the story in permanent form; discusses her sister and Theodore Crane's visit; mentions family matters.
  - Olivia L. Clemens, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1889 January 13; ALS, 3 p. (Box 3)
    Distressed Koto has been ill; says she should learn to be lazy until she is better; reports brother-in-law Theodore Crane improving slowly; passing mention that Mrs. Cabell is ill at Charles Dudley Warner's home.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Edward Howard House, 1889 March 19; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses contract with [Abby Sage?] Richardson to dramatize The Prince and the Pauper; says if there was a contract with House, he would try to straighten out the problem; recalls House's initial efforts to dramatize the book, his own lack of interest in the project, and his impression that House had abandoned the project since he did not mention it; had always wished the book to be dramatized and would have preferred House to do it; suggested to Mrs. Richardson that she might get help from him.
  - Robert Green Ingersoll, New York, to "My dear friend" ( Mark Twain ), Hartford, CT, 1889 March 29; TL, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses House's claim to have a contract to dramatize The Prince and the Pauper and asks for Twain's version of events.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Augustin Daly, 1889 April 5; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Is obliged to Daly and Miss Rehan; remarks his own status with his children rests not on his own works, but from the fact he knows Miss Rehan and Mr. Drew personally.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to [Robert Underwood] Johnson, 1889 August 3; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Says [Dan] Beard is the artist; would soon as have the article in the November issue (of The Century ) as in the December issue; suggests he talk to [Fred J.] Hall; thinks Beard could skip ahead and make pictures for another part of the book; thinks he will do nice work. M.T.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to The Century Editors, 1889 August 7; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Has done his best to get it to them in time for November issue; will ask Fred J. Hall to hurry Dan Beard to finish the pictures. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Elmira, NY, to Fred J. Hall, 1889 August 20; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Agrees proof must follow his own punctuation absolutely; asks Hall to instruct Chatto to issue in London December. 6, in Canada December. 8, and in United States December. 10. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Unknown, 1890 March 17; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Not expecting to be in London this year but might be there anyway; has tried to write things he would like to tell English workingmen but without success; will keep theme in mind and perhaps do it in future. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Hartford, CT, to Fred J. Hall, 1890 December 27; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Expresses bitter opinion of lawyer Whitford retained for a suit by Charles L. Webster & Company; suggests another lawyer if any further lawsuits with Gill. S.L.C.
  - [Jane Lampton Clemens] to [Samuel E. Moffett ?], [before 1890]; AN, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Will come with a big red apple for him and bring him home; then they will go to 14th street depot to see the locomotive, wheel, and water ball. With grocery list on verso.
  - R.F. Blodgett, Pratt & Whitney Company, to Mark Twain, for Mark Twain and James W. Paige, 1891 January 10; TLS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Cover letter for 2 monthly statements.
  - James W. Paige to Mark Twain, 1891 March 18; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Requests Twain pay memorandum he encloses from Pratt & Whitney Company, which he showed Twain in January in accordance with their agreement.
  - Mark Twain to James W. Paige with ANS, 1891 March 19; AL, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Reminds him that since he declined to sign a contract, Twain had said he would not lend Paige any more money; is returning bill to Pratt & Whitney Company. ANS at bottom states this letter is copy of reply to Paige's letters of March 18. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to Joseph T. Goodman, [1891 April]; ALS, 3 p. (Box 3)
    Discusses his new and less satisfactory contract for the Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company; is working on new book; says publishing beginning to be profitable but must make $50,000 for the company until January when Library of American Literature begins to return dividends. M.T.] (ALS has 1/3 of pg.2 trimmed out and glued to another sheet)
  - Mark Twain, Frankfurt, to Chatto & Windus, 1891 October 7; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Requests copy of a cookbook be sent to his Berlin address, which he asks they not divulge. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Berlin, to Rudolf Lindau, Berlin, [1891] December 11; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Thanks him for dinner; is seasoning cob pipe in whisky for Lindau's nephew; has lecture engagement in Dresden. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Berlin, to Rudolf Lindau, [1891] December 24; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Sends a photograph (not present), taken about eight years ago, of himself; mentions his own rheumatism; will look for photo of Lindau. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to [Fred J.] Hall, [1891] December 26; ANS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Asks Hall to renew his letter of credit which expires January. 7. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Berlin, to [Rudolf] Lindau, [late 1891]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Delighted to accept invitation. S.L.C.
  - Robert McClure, London, to Mark Twain, Paris, with ANS 1892 March 8 Mark Twain and ANS n.d. Mark Twain to Fred J. Hall, 1892 March 2; TLS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Acknowledges receipt of manuscript of fifth article; explains Charles L. Webster & Company cable; sorry Twain has been ill; at bottom, ANS 1892 March 8 Mark Twain says article mentioned above concerns Berlin and is the sixth article; at bottom, second ANS n.d. Mark Twain asks Fred J. Hall to save letter as proof of completion of the McClure contract. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Menton, France, to Mrs. Charles Fairchild, Boston, Mass., 1892 March 8; ALS, 2 p. (w/env) (Box 3)
    Says she does not need to explain; briefly discusses William Dean Howells ' grief over his daughter Winnie; briefly mentions Thomas Bailey Aldrich's and Oliver Wendell Holmes ' ageing. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to [Catherine C.] Bronson, 1892 May 25; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Thanks for the books; had hoped to see her before leaving; had called with Olivia and daughters to say goodbye but missed her. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Florence, to U.S. Vice-Consul General Mr. Hogue, Frankfurt, 1892 October 14; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Thanks him for arrival of the rest of Tom Sawyer Abroad and the closing pages of The Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson; plans to start working when settled down in Florence; comments unfavorably on The Century article on Columbus's portrait; Clara has received one trunk but two are lost somewhere. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain to Fred J. Hall, 1892 December 26; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Agrees with Carey to change "Royston's" name and village's name; suggests Hall contact Carnegie about borrowing money to publish Library of American Literature to a thousand sets per month; wants his "Mental Telegraphy" in the book even if something else must be dropped; has received the "St. Nick proposition" to "split payment" and has written "all right" to Hall and [Mary Mapes] Dodge. S.L.C.
  - M[ollie] Stotts C[lemens] to Unknown, [ca. 1892]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Fragment. Good wishes to them all; will have something for them someday, perhaps soon.
  - Mark Twain, at sea on Kaiser Wilhelm II, to C[hatto] & W[indus], 1893 May 23; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Asks to have a copy of a volume with "The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County" sent to Captain Stormer at Twain's expense. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, [New York], to Unknown, 1893 June 3; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Requests that recipient put Twain's money in the Mount Morris Bank, including money from royalties until they can see whether recipient can sell Twain's interest in an unspecified business. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to Fred J. Hall, 1893 July 19; ALS, 1 p.
    Thanks him for letter; cannot answer it but will send the notes, "as August is not far away." S.L.C.] (tipped in The Gilded Age, Barrett PS 1311 .A1 1874 copy 5)
  - Olivia L. Clemens to Mary Robinson Shipman with ANS [1893 August 11] Mark Twain to [Mary Robinson Shipman], ALS, 10 p. (Box 3)
    Had enjoyed seeing the Shipmans in Europe very much and looks forward to seeing all of them back in Hartford; comments on the joy of meeting friends in Europe; sends regards to Judge [Nathaniel] Shipman; enjoyed Annie Eliot Trumbull's "White Birches"; mentions the Hillyers and Sally Dunham; wishes they (the Clemens) might see the Chicago Fair. With ANS [1893 August 11] Mark Twain to [Mary Robinson Shipman ], says note was "smuggled" into Olivia's letter and jokes she is concerned about tautology in her letter. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain to [George Wheeler] Hinman, 1893 September 18; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Thanks from him and his daughter; sends book of his which is full of statistics and should help correspondent's next edition. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, New York, to [Richard Watson] Gilder, [1893] November 6; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    No longer gives prices for his articles because when he did so before, editors said he under priced himself. S.L.C.
  - The Players Club ( Mark Twain et al.) to Sir Henry Irving, 1893 November 13; ALS, 3 p. (Box 3)
    Dinner invitation from the Club signed by Laurence Hutton, George Parsons Lathrop, Brander Matthews, Mark Twain (S.L.C. signature), Richard Watson Gilder, Charles Dudley Warner, William Dean Howells, Francis Lathrop, F. D. Millet, William M. Laffan, Joseph Jefferson, H.C. Banner, R. Swain Gifford, Charles Fairchild, Thomas Bailey Aldrich.
  - Mark Twain to Clarence C. Buel, [1893] December 18; ALS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Says he has lost his voice and has doctor's orders not to use it; asks Buel to try to postpone next day's lecture. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, The Players Club, to Unknown ["Theuerste Fraulein"], 1893 December 25; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Promises to come to her play January 10 if he is still in the country; has been in Chicago for 3 days "visiting the ruins." S.L.C.
  - Arthur Stedman to Stone and Kimball, 1894 February 16; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Re a manuscript by the sister of Edmond Picton.
  - Mark Twain to "Dear Sirs", [1894 March 3]; AN, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Offers other investors one-quarter interest in Twain contract with Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company with autograph draft of letter.
  - Unknown to Mark Twain, 1894 March 3; TL (copy), 1 p. (Box 3)
    Re sale of Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company stock from pools.
  - Urban H. Broughton, Paige Compositor Manufacturing Company, Chicago, IL, to Mark Twain, 1894 March 8; TLS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Has received two copies from Twain of Paige Compositor contract; will execute and return them to Henry H. Rogers.
  - Mark Twain, Paris, to Fred J. Hall, Tarrytown, NY, 1894 June 1; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Unable to help him since "the whole business is in the hands of creditors"; discusses past problem with a bank, his indebtedness, and Hall's trouble; mentions Franklin G. Whitmore; will see Hall in July. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, Etretat, Normandy, to J. Henry Harper with AN by J. Henry Harper, 1894 September 11-12; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    Reports arrival of manuscript ( Personal Recollections of Joan of Arc ); wants Harper to draft an order requiring the compositor and proof-reader to follow copy exactly; mentions The Century proofreader who tampered with his punctuation in The Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson in the manuscript before sending it to the printer; intends to add to manuscript 1200 words, including a three stanza song; thanks for the books; encloses copy of extra material and notes where it should be located in manuscript; not all the Personal Recollections of Joan of Arc came as manuscript was opened at French custom house. S.L.C. With AN signed J. Henry Harper on verso of p. 3 says Mr. Alden sent complete copy of manuscript and difficulty can be resolved if Twain indicates where his manuscript ends.
  - Stern & Rushmore to Henry H. Rogers, 1894 October 17; TLS, 1 p. (Box 3)
    Acknowledges receipt of $500 check for Mark Twain's account.
  - Bainbridge Colby to Frank E. Bliss, 1894 November 27; ALS, 2 p. (Box 3)
    Offers him opportunity to bid on the plates on condition terms can be arranged for continuing publication; will transmit offer to Henry H. Rogers who represents Olivia L. Clemens. With typed list of prices of the plates of a dozen Mark Twain books.
  - Mark Twain, Paris, to William Thomas Stead, [1894] November 30; ALS, 4 p. (Box 3)
    About conclusions of four hand-writing analysts and his reaction to their analyses. M.T.